<section id = "JAPANESE SAILORS' SONGS">
 
<songTitle str = "POPULAR JAPANESE BARCAROLLE" originLocation = "Japan" subject = "sl"></songTitle> 
 

<commentary>A GULF not to be spanned divides the harmonies of the 
east from those of the west. The Japanese seem to dislike 
our music, and to find it as wanting (according to their 
ideas) in harmony, as we find theirs mysterious and dis- 
 
The music of the " Empire of the Rising Sun," like most 
of its arts and sciences, is mainly Chinese and Corean, and 
its theory has, therefore, the usual spirit of mystical Chinese 
speculation, which, basing the forces and phenomena of 
nature upon the number 5, declares that, as sounds belong 

to such phenomena, there must be five tones ; but in stringed 
instruments, which are all they have in Japan, they make 
use of chromatic divisions, although the five tones alone 
are recognized officially. 

Seeing what an important place Japan now takes amongst 
the maritime countries of the world, it may not be unin- 
teresting to attempt some study of the songs used by its 
sailors. From the little I have been able to gather, I should 
conclude that they very much resemble those used by our 
own blue-jackets, or rather the occasions on which they 
are used are similar, their object namely, unity and regu- 
larity in work is the same, and the variety of subject ; but 
there the likeness ceases, for, as I have said, the gulf is 
not to be spanned that divides our and Eastern music. 

It is only on board of their merchant-vessels that 
singing is allowed, the Japanese Navy not permitting 
the practice on the men-of-war, a band taking the place of 
the chanty. This probably consists of the " sho," which 
seems to correspond to our organ, but only in so far as it 
has pipes. A " koto " also will be found, an instrument 
not unlike the violin, and probably a "fuye," which is a 
Japanese flute. Of course there are many varieties of 
these three, but I believe they will always be found in a 
Japanese orchestra. The "sho" and the "fuye"" have 
tremendous power, and if it be true that silence is a 
characteristic of nature in Japan (singing-birds being very 
rare, and only the deep, troubled tones of the crows being 
heard), what an extraordinary effect this most penetrating 
orchestra must produce in the stillness that reigns in the 
waters round the empire. Like most sailors, the Japanese 
seem to take great pride in handing down to posterity the 
noble deeds of their countrymen, and the bravery of the 
chieftains who held sway in feudal times forms the theme 
of many of their sea-songs. 

Almost all these songs are in very slow time, and nearly 
all are set in a minor key. I think I am not far wrong in 
stating that this is the case in every kind of Japanese 

music (at least, in all that I have heard). The sailors' songs 
are mostly chromatic passages with but little variation. 
An occasional lowering or raising of a tone is sometimes 
unexpectedly introduced, in some a continued series of 
shakes produces an extraordinarily weird effect, especially 
as the minor key is here, as elsewhere, adopted. 

To my idea their rowing-songs are decidedly the most 
pleasing of all ; they have really a very charming effect. 
Musically speaking, they may not be very pretentious, but 
they may be taken as an indication of the style and cha- 
racter of the nation they belong to. They are sung on the 
" sampans," partially triangular-shaped boats, something 
like the salmon -fisher's punt used on certain British rivers. 
They are sculled, not what we should call rowed, by two 
or four men with very heavy oars, and they stand up, 
using their thighs to rest the oars upon. I give the notes 
of one of these as accurately as I can, the words I am 
unable to translate. A very distinguished member of the 
Japanese naval college, perfectly acquainted with our 
language, assures me they have no meaning, that is, none 
that can be translated : </commentary>

<songTitle id = "JAPANESE ROWING SONG" originLocation = "Japan" subject = "sl"><songTitle>
 
<lyrics>Hou- ra Hoi Sa - no San - ya Hou - yei - ya.</lyrics>

<commentary>The chorus is to give emphasis to certain strokes, and is 
repeated alternately with the solo without any change of 
either words or tune. 

Dice seem to play a very important part on board 
Japanese vessels. The dice-box is regarded as an essential. 
Perhaps I am wrong in giving the word as dice ; it may 
be rather the game of " go," which Miss Bird, in her book, 
"Unbeaten Tracks in Japan," refers to as being such a 
great resource in the country. It is played with 1 80 white 
discs cut from a species of cockle-shell, and 181 black ones 

made from a black pebble ; the board is divided into 361 
squares, and the game consists in trying to enclose a 
certain space and preventing the opponent from doing the 
same. In days gone by, some horrible legend about instant 
death to the vanquished in this game was current. To 
think of this fatal gambling at sea, brings to one's mind 
that horrible phantom ship in Coleridge's "Ancient Mariner " : </commentary>

<lyrics>" The naked hulk alongside came, 
And the twain were casting dice ; 
The game is done : ' Fve won ! I've won ! ' 
Quoth she, and whistles thrice." </lyrics>

<commentary>Many harbours, as in our country, claim for their own 
certain chanties. Some of these become popular, and are 
soon heard all over Japan or wherever the Japanese flag is 
hoisted, but in some harbours the prerogative of singing 
them is retained. There is one sung when lifting heavy 
cargo, peculiar to the harbour of Matsumai, although its 
popularity amongst the sailors of other ports has led to its 
becoming an established Japanese sea-song. Matsumai is 
also the name of a great chieftain who lived in feudal 
times, and was a man of such renowned bravery that no 
one could beat him. He seems to have had no rival in 
strength, and has been handed down to posterity as a naval 
Samson. It is also sung when pulling the ropes, though 
more generally when lifting any heavy weight. While the 
solo is being sung, the rest hold themselves in readiness 
either to pull or to heave, as the case may be. </commentary>

<songTitle str= "MATSUMAI" originLocation = "Japan" subject = "sl"></songTitle> (JAPANESE SAILORS' SONG.) 
 
<lyrics>Mat - su mai sa - ma -de - mo yaa yai. 
 
Yat - to Ro - se - i Yon - ya 

Leader. " Matsumai, sama, demo, 

Nindzu niya Kanawanu yoitana. 

Chorus. Ariya, ariya, yoitoko, yoitokona, riya, riya, riya. 
Leader. Medeta, medetano, yo-a-yei. 
Chorus. Yatukosei, yomyama ! 
Leader. Medeta, medetano, wakamatu. 
Chorus. Ariya, ariya, riya, riya, riya."</lyrics>

<commentary>The same notes serve throughout the song, which is a 
recital and sort of chant of praise of the chieftain Mat- 
 
Then there is a short song for when they are scrubbing 
or, as we say, holystoning the decks. It is sung in chorus, 
and has, at least to us, no meaning. It seems to help 
them, however, in their work, and, as far as I have been 
able to learn, is the only one they use for this purpose.</commentary>

<songTitle str = "JAPANESE CHORUS USED WHEN SCRUBBING THE DECKS" originLocation = "Japan" subject = "sl"></songTitle>
  
<lyrics>Yoito Ivor - as a - mo Yass - kin - ya.</lyrics>

<commentary>Another song that Japanese sailors sing, and one that I 
believe is quite peculiar to themselves, is the song sung 
during a calm at sea, when work is for the time being sus- 
pended. A favourite one is about Nagareyama, a place 
celebrated, in Japan, for its wine, and the song is descrip- 
tive of the sailors taking this wine away to distant countries 
and exchanging it for the gold and treasures thereof. It 
appears that they have a curious custom of placing near 
the masts, when a ship is launched, some maidenhair-fern 
and rice. The maidenhair is looked upon as something 
almost sacred in Japan ; and rice, as is well known, is to the 
Japanese what fish is to the Esquimaux, or oatmeal to the 
Scotchman therefore, I suppose, they are chosen as 
omens of good luck, to be, as they call them, " the gods 
of the ship." This custom is also alluded to in the song 
 
Nagareyama ; it is sung throughout in chorus, only the 
songs that accompany heavy work being in the form of 
alternate soli and chorus. 

I give a few of the notes which will show the style of 
the music ; it is to our ideas monotonous, as there are 
many verses and only these few tones to set them to : </commentary>

<songTitle str = "NAGAREYMNA. (SONG SUNG DURING A CALM AT SEA)" originLocation = "Japan" subject = "sl"></songTitle>
   
<commentary>The first and third lines and second and fourth of this 
song are sung by the same men, not as soli but in 
chorus : </commentary>

<lyrics>" Nagareyma, naggarete ritaka, 
Nagareyma nagaretewo ronai, 
 
Medetaimonowa ofunadama 
Asa, oroshi banniwa, koganeo </lyrics>
 
<commentary>In the Gulf of Yedo, the populous coast is very impres- 
sive thousands of fishing-boats skimming here and there, 
sampans being sculled in all directions the general appear- 
ance is colourless, the sea is pale, the coast grey, the 
boats are pale (their hulls being unpainted wood, and their 
sails pure white duck), whilst overhead, 13,080 feet above 
the sea, gleams in its dazzling pallor the wondrous truncated 
cone of snow, the sacred mountain of " Fujisan," so dear 
to the Japanese. The air and water seem motionless, the 
mist hangs still and ghost-like, grey clouds rest on a bluish 
sky, the .reflections of the white sails of the fishing-boats 
scarcely seem to quiver ; it is all (says Miss Bird, in her 

poetical description) 1 " so pale and wan and peaceful, that 
the very turbulence of crumpled foam which we leave 
behind us, and our noisy throbbing progress, seem a boister- 
ous intrusion upon sleeping Asia." It is with a scene like 
this before one on the silence of nature reigning around, 
that one can imagine the song " Nagareyama " rising from 
some of the idle becalmed vessels around ; if anything had 
been wanting to complete the weird effect, it would be 
found in this mournful, monotonous dirge-like tune, so 
suggestive of the calm that gave birth to it. A Japanese 
vessel at a time like this resembles Shelley's exquisite 
description of the " Boat on the Serchio " : </commentary>

<lyrics>" Our boat is asleep in Serchio's stream, 
Its sails are folded like thoughts in a dream, 
The helm sways idly, hither and thither/' </lyrics>

<commentary>Japanese sailors and fishermen, like those of every other 
nation, are great believers in the supernatural, and many 
strange customs, curious legends, and beliefs of sailor- 
lore are rife amongst them. Miss Bird says a fisherman 
never considers it lucky to meet a priest (bonze) on his 
way to his boat ; it is considered lucky to dream of sailing 
in a ship. The Japanese have a tradition that their 
ancestors came from the skies in a boat, and another to 
the effect that fish are the embodiment of the souls of 
naval officers. Both Japanese and Chinese sailors consider 
it a good omen to cross the bows of a foreign vessel, and 
frequently give great trouble in crowded channels, and 
incur considerable danger from this cause. 

Speaking of mermaids, Mr. Bassett, in his recently 
published book of " Legends and Superstitions of the Sea 
and of Sailors," says : " Japan is, however, the headquarters 
of these coy maidens." Here an old Dutch navigator 
obtained the first " veritable " mermaid, and they may still 
be procured of ingenious natives ; numbers have been  

shown in museums, &amp;c., deftly made by uniting a child's 
head to a fish's body. 

At Bartholomew fair, in 1825, there was exhibited a mer- 
maid obtained by a Dutch ship from Japan, and the 
Ottoman minister to Paris, in 1840, related that he had 
seen a veritable sea-woman brought from Eastern seas. 
They have a legend relating that a mermaid prophesied 
an epidemic. 

I must not close these few remarks on Japanese seamen 
without some mention of the Ainos, that tribe of simple, 
indolent savages, whose life is so made up of the sea that 
one can handly disassociate them in one's mind. The 
Ainos are the aborigines of the Yezo ; the race is gradually 
becoming extinct, scarcely to the sorrow of the Japanese, 
who regard them with feelings of great contempt. They 
live only on the coasts, and subsist solely on what they reap 
from the harvest of the sea. As they are without written 
characters, minus any literature, and apparently most un- 
willing to give any information concerning themselves 
even to those who can understand them it is almost 
impossible to learn anything of their music, or even if they 
have any ; but from an account given, in a description of 
them, of a musical instrument they use, something like 
a guitar, made of three or six strings formed of whales' 
sinews cast upon the shore, we may infer that they do 
sing and probably use this most original instrument to 
accompany their crooning ditties. That these will be wild, 
unintelligible performances to us I doubt not, but that 
they can offer more extraordinary phases of musical 
history than the general music of Japan I can scarcely 
believe. It may be that the lonely Aino's song, with only 
nature for audience, may partake more of the true sweet- 
ness which marks all her melodies, for the very boom of 
the surf, the strange cries of the sea-birds, the hoarse notes 
of the audacious crows, are all in themselves complete and 
perfect studies of harmony, for nature when left to herself 
never produces discords, either in sound or colour. 

And now I must close my remarks on the blue-jackets 
of the " Empire of the Rising Sun." Incomplete and 
it may be inaccurate they are, but the distance that 
separates our world from theirs, the scanty communication 
that up till a few years ago existed between us, and the 
general ignorance shown in their country, government, and 
social life, may suffice to explain the difficulty of obtaining 
facts concerning so small a portion of the history of a 
people as their sailors' songs. With the impetus given to 
matters maritime at home and abroad, the undoubted zeal 
and ability displayed by its enterprising engineers, the 
magnitude and importance of its naval college, we may 
expect ere long to see Japan in the front rank, if not fore- 
most, of the maritime nations of the world. </commentary> </section>

<section id = "NILE BOATMEN'S CHANTS">

THE BOATMEN'S SONGS ON THE NILE. 

<quote>"THE main streets crossed each other at right angles, 
from wall to wall with beautiful breadth, and to the length, 
if it may be credited, of nearly nine miles. At their ex- 
tremities the gates looked out on the gilded barges of the 
hill of fleets at sea, under full sail, on a harbour that 
sheltered navies, and a lighthouse that was the mariner's 
star, and the wonder of the world." Such is Campbell's 
description of Alexandria in Mehemet Ali's time. A long 
line of windmills on a sandy ridge, the new lighthouse and 
palace built by the present pasha, and the tall column of 
Diocletian, the only visible wreck of the ancient city, are 
the few prominent objects which rise above the dead level 
of the sea. 

" The entrance to the harbour is difficult, but its spacious 
area is thronged with ships of war, steamers, merchantmen, 
and all the smaller craft incident to extended traffic. Yet 
the first view of Alexandria, full as it is of historical remi- 
niscences, is, in all other respects, more unimposing than 
that of any other city on the Mediterranean."</quote> 

<commentary>This is the description given of it by Mr. Bartlett, in 1845, m his "Nile Boat"
 
The boatmen of the Nile are not less pious in their way 
than the rest of the Egyptian Arabs, or less accustomed to 
the use of those religious forms so characteristic of Mahome- 
dan intercourse. Their mutual salutations are all prayers, 
like those of Boaz and his reapers : " Peace be upon you ' 

" God be with you " " May God receive you into 
Paradise," are common expressions interchanged between 
passing crews, and they never pass, even at a distance, 
without saluting one another. The songs with which they 
encourage one another at the labour of the oar are in a 
similar strain of invocation, and often have a very beautiful 
effect. The Rets leads the air, and the boatmen sing in 
chorus, increasing the fervour of their chant and the vigour 
of their labours almost to frenzy, with the difficulty to be 
surmounted. Nothing can be done with them without fre- 
quent presents of meat or money. Dr. Olin says that " Gra- 
tuities of all sorts, in money, food, or any other form, are 
denominated ' bucksheesh.' This is the first word in the 
language which a traveller is likely to learn, and the least 
tenacious memory is in no danger of forgetting it. If you 
speak kindly to the Reis or sailors, or even look upon them 
with an unclouded brow, they demand this species of tribute. 
If the wind proves favourable or we succeed in driving them 
to their work a little earlier than usual, or in keeping under 
sail till the sun is fairly out of sight, it is sure to be hailed 
as an auspicious occasion when we may testify our appro- 
bation by a gratuity. In all their narratives they have no 
other standard of excellence than the amount of bucksheesh 
bestowed upon them. The man who has given them 
liberal bucksheesh, no matter if he has flogged them every 
day, is always excellent. All others are evil in their 
 
The singing of the sailors on the Nile has frequently 
been noticed and described. This usually consists of alter- 
nate solo and chorus in short phrases, and varies with the 
nature of the occupation in which the men happen to be 
engaged. Thus one particular air is sung when they 
shift the sails ; another when the boat strikes on a sandy 
bank, and they are working to set it afloat again ; a 
third when the wind is favourable and they give themselves 
up to singing con amore, a fourth when approaching a 
village, and so on. Several efforts have been made to pro- 

cure more specimens of these Nile choruses, but unsuccess- 
fully ; I have met with one or two, however, which I give. 
The following is a sample of the songs used when approach- 
ing a village :</commentary>
 
<lyrics>Hel - - - - il fa-i- urn val - la-dac ia 

He!. 

He ! He ! il fa - ium Ca - la - dac ia - rum. 

Bi-iu-tu - ey Va-lad - al - mali - ruo 
 
He - li - sa !  
 
Ca - la - dal - man ruh. 

He! li - sa! </lyrics>

<commentary>The next specimen is, I believe, one of those songs used 
when the wind is favourable, and good temper prevails with 
the crew. It is taken .from Mr. McGregor's " Collection of 
Eastern Music." </commentary>
 
<songTitle str = "CHORUS. 532" originLocation = "Egypt" subject = "sl"><songTitle> 

<lyrics>Yul - la 
 
Yul - la nai - ly Ya sa - laa - my, 

Yul - la nai - ly Ya sa - laa- my. 

Yul- la nai- ly Ya sa - laa- my, 

pin- o - ran.   

Na- li - a- mo san-kib 
  
Yul- la nai - ly 

Ya sa - laa-my, 

fis nae - 

Yul - la nai - ly Ya sa - laa - my. </lyrics>

<commentary>I can only give the words of one of the modern Egyptian 
love-songs, which follow, and which are both recognized 
favourites with the boatmen of the stately river :</commentary>

<lyrics>Doos ya bel - lee, doos ya bel - - lee, Doos yd 

bel - lee ; Doos ya bel - lee, doos ya bel - lee, doos ya </lyrics>
  
<commentary>At the head of the pleasure-boats of the Nile a man 
usually stood, with a long pole in his hand, to sound every 
now and then, and to prevent the boat running upon any 
of the numerous sand-banks in the river (which, from their 
often changing at the time of the inundation, are not always 
known to the most skilful pilot) ; a precaution adopted 
sometimes too late by the modern boatmen of the Nile. 
The same weird sort of chant or plumbing song is used for 
this as by the Lascars on the Brahmaputra. 

The papyrus boats, mentioned by Pliny, must have been 
the same as the " Vessels of bulrushes," spoken of in Isaiah ; 
indeed they are frequently alluded to by ancient writers. 
Plutarch describes Isis as going in search of the body of 
Osiris " through the fenny country, in a bark made of the 
papyrus, whence it is supposed that persons using boats of 
this description are never attacked by crocodiles, out of 
fear and respect for the goddess." There is a song men- 
tioned in connection with the building of these same boats, 
but it does not appear to have been put on record, as far as 
I have been able to ascertain.</commentary></section>

<section id = "INDIAN WATER-SONGS">

<commentary>IN the Rig- Veda, or the sacred books of the Brahmans, 
several hymns are addressed to the waters (Ap), some to 
Nadi (the rivers), and some to Maruts (the storms) ; so 
the connection between Indian music and the world of 
waters is one of great antiquity and classical association. 

In Mr. W. D. Whitney's article on the Veda? he gives 
amongst other portions of the work a few of the hymns 
to the great rivers : one, an account of the propitiation 
of the two branches of the Indus the modern Beas and 
Sutlej by songs and praises from the Saint Viqvdmitra&amp;gt; 
chief priest of the Bharatas.</commentary>

<subheading id = "VigvAMITRA AND THE RIVERS"></subheading>

<subheading>Rig-Veda, III. 33.</subheading>

<songTitle str = "VlCVAMITRA" originLocation = "India" subject = "sl"></songTitle>
 
<lyrics>I. " Eager, from out the bosom of the mountains, 
A pair of courses like, let loose and running, 
Like two bright mother-kine their offspring fondling, 
Vipa,9 and (Jutudri haste with their waters. 

3. " I've come to this most mother-like of rivers ; 

We stand beside the broad, auspicious Vipa9, 
Like mother-kine fondling their calves together, 
Unto a common home they're moving onward." </lyrics>

<songTitle str = "THE RIVERS" originLocation = "India" subject = "sl"></songTitle> 

<lyrics>4. " Thus move we onward, swelling with our waters, 

To find a home that's by the gods appointed ; 

Our headlong, forward rush no man can hinder. 
What seeks the sage, calling upon us rivers ? "</lyrics>

<commentary>The hymn is a long one ; the verses alternately attributed 
to the saint and the rivers.</commentary>

<heading id = "INDIAN ROWING AND BOAT-SONGS"></heading> 

<commentary>The sailors of the province of Sinde, in Hindustan, have 
their peculiar songs, as seafaring men generally have. 
They are Mohammedans, and the songs used by them 
when they are pulling their ropes and sails often contain 
expressions of reverence to their saints. The translator of 
the following specimen of these songs praises its simplicity 
and beauty of expression in its original language :</commentary>

<lyrics>Pull, oh ! pull ! 
Raise your shoulders, 
Press your feet. 
The boat will sail, 
The steersman's a warrior. 
The mast is tall : 
Beat the drum ; 
The port is attained. 
Use your strength ; 
By the favour of God, 
By the saints' assistance, 
She is a pretty boat : 
The water is deep, 
She will harbour in safety. 
Of King Acbar, 
By the favour of God."</lyrics>

<commentary>Sirens existed in Indian waters and lulled mariners to 
sleep by their songs. In speaking of them, in his "Legends 
and Superstitions of the Sea and of Sailors," Mr. Bassett 
says, " They represent the white and shining surf, whose 
harmonious murmurs and seductive brightness allures, but 
destroys the mariner who attempts to land." </commentary>

<lyrics>" Sometimes upon the diamond rocks they leant, 

Sometimes they sat upon the flowery lea 
That sloped toward the wave, and ever sent 
Shrill music o'er the sea. 

" One piped, one sang, one swept the golden lyre, 

And thus to forge and ring a threefold chain 
Of linked harmony, the three conspire, 
O'er land and hoary main"</lyrics> 

<commentary>The following is a specimen of the Indian rowing-songs 
used on the " Rio Negro " in South America : 

The following song is a sort of labour-song or chant of 
the Madras boatmen. The grain-ships are unloaded at 
Madras, and the cargo taken by Musulah boats ; these are 
pushed through the surf, and it is then that this song or 
chant may be heard ; when they near the ship again, the 
surf being deeper and more force being required, they break 
into the Ya-Allah, Ya-Allah, Ya-Allah, in sharp, almost 
spasmodic tones, and continue till they are through it.</commentary>

<lyrics>Ya - al - lah, Ya - al - lab, Ya - al - lah. </lyrics>

<commentary>The Madras boat-song I give next I obtained from 
Dr. Crotch's " Specimens " (No. 326). It is sung by the 
steersman and crew : </commentary>

<songTitle str="DANDEE SONG" originLocation="India" subject="sl">DANDEE SONG. (BENGALESE BOATMEN.)</songTitle>

<commentary>
The two following songs are both favourites with the boatmen:
</commentary>

<lyrics>
Mo-ney makes the mare to go, Whe-ther she has legs or no ;
My old mare she would not go, Till I got the mo- ney O !

1. Mo-ney makes the mare to go, Whe-ther she has legs or no ;

2. My old mare she would not go, Till I got the mo- ney O !

1. Lame, blind, or spa- vin'd O ! Nev- er mind, she's sure to go ;

2. Then the corn it made her go, And she got quite frisk- y O !

1. Lame, blind, or spa- vin'd O ! Nev- er mind, she's sure to go.

2. Then the corn it made her go, And she got quite frisk- y O !

3. " Money makes the mare to go,
Whether she has legs or no ;
Money makes the mare to go,
Whether she has legs or no.

Broken-winded, old and slow,
Give her corn and plenty, O !
Broken-winded, old, and slow,
Give her corn and plenty, O !

4. " Without money here below,
We must look for toil and woe ;
Without money here below,
We must look for toil and woe.
Such is life at present, O !
What it may be, who can know ?
Such is life at present, O !
What it may be, who can know ? "
</lyrics>

<lyrics>
1. The voyage of life is oft- en rough, The wind is sel- dom fair,
And tho' the morn be bright e- nough It oft- en ends in care :
Then let us sing and mer- ry be And drive dull care a- way,
For who can tell what may oc- cur Be- fore an- o- ther day !
Ah, who can tell what may oc- cur Be- fore an- o- ther day.

2. " Why should we not this life enjoy ?
It cannot be for long ;
It's time enough when pleasures cloy,
To give up mirth and song.
Then let us sing and merry be,
For who can tell what may occur
Before another day ?
Ah ! who can tell what may occur
Before another day ?

3. " This world they say is a world of woe,
Yet no one wants to leave ;
And if grim death his face should show,
We'd beg for a reprieve.
Then let us sing and merry be,
And drive dull care away.
For who can tell what may occur
Before another day ?
Ah ! who can tell what may occur
Before another day ? "
</lyrics>

<commentary>
The Taza b-Taza is one of the most popular songs sung by the Indian boatmen, although it is of Persian origin, written by the poet Hafiz, and will be found in the Goolistan "Rose Garden."
</commentary>

<songTitle str="TAZA B-TAZA" originLocation="India" subject="sl">TAZA B-TAZA.</songTitle>

<subheading>INDIAN VERSION.</subheading>

<lyrics>
Taza b-taza-no-b-no,
Mootrel b-koosh newar bego
Taza b-taza-no-b-no,
Bur zai hiaat bziada-oo,
Taza b-taza-no-b-no.

Jillee millee paronee-ah
Ja men (ne) nudea.
</lyrics>

<subheading>ENGLISH VERSION.</subheading>

<lyrics>
Fresh and fresh and new and new,
Oh morning breeze ! in passing o'er that fairy's village,
Carry to her the compliments of Hafiz,
Fresh and fresh and new and new.

Freely now is the time to go and bathe,
Jump into the river hand in hand.
</lyrics>

<commentary>
The words of the "Bhiertpoor Dirge," which follow, are Bengalese ; and the air to which they are set, although of a very plaintive nature, is a great favourite with the Indian boatmen.
</commentary>

<songTitle str="BHIERTPOOR DIRGE" originLocation="India" subject="sl">BHIERTPOOR DIRGE.</songTitle>

<subheading>INDIAN VERSION.</subheading>

<lyrics>
Kyoo Durzun Lai se,
Holi Kelenkoayah Lai (Sahib),
Pytchparri ka bia bun golee topee
Rung ahur Kloon se bunnia ah.
Ai Durzun Lai koomeer ab ayah,
HoliKelen ko ayah Lai (Sahib).
</lyrics>

<subheading>ENGLISH VERSION.</subheading>

<lyrics>
Say to Durzun Lai,
That the Lord Sahib has arrived,
To play holi with him.
For squirts, he has brought
Mortars and guns ;
For yellow dye and red powder,
He will have blood.
Ah ! Durzun Lai, the alligator has—
The Lord Sahib has come to play.
</lyrics>

<commentary>
The waters of the Brahmaputra are so shallow, owing to the sand banks, that the leadsmen are bound to plumb all the way up to Dibrugarh, the head-waters of the Brahmaputra, which go up amongst the Himalayas. The monotonous chant for such it is of the leadsman "Teen bom milla ne," or "Three fathoms and no bottom," deserves, I think, to be mentioned, if only to commend the patience with which it is almost unceasingly repeated for the three thousand miles of the voyage.
</commentary>

<songTitle str="TEEN BOM MILLA NE" originLocation="India" subject="sl">"Teen Bom Mil-la Ne."</songTitle>

<lyrics>
Sarra — Half.
Ek to bom — One fathom.
Do to bom — Two fathoms.
Teen bom milla ne — Three fathoms and no bottom.
</lyrics>

<commentary>
This is chanted by one man, who is relieved every few hours — a fact I was glad to learn. 

The flats generally have on board forty sailors or 
" Lascars," the " Sarang " or native captain, the " Secunna" 
or quartermaster, and a European commander. </commentary></section>

<section id="FROM_CHINA_TO_PERU">FROM CHINA TO PERU.>

<heading>FISHERMEN'S, BOATMEN'S, AND SAILORS' CHANTS AND SONGS.</heading>

<quote>
"The deeps have music soft and low
When winds awake the airy spry,
It lures, lures me on to go
And see the land where corals lie."
</quote>

<quote>
"All human race, from China to Peru,
Pleasure, howe'er disguised by art, pursue."

"Let observation with extensive view
Survey mankind from China to Peru."
</quote>

<songTitle str="CHINESE SONG" originLocation="China" subject="sl">CHINESE SONG.</songTitle>

<commentary>Moderate, con sentimento tranquillo.</commentary>

<songTitle str="CHINESE BOATMAN'S SONG" originLocation="China" subject="sl">CHINESE BOATMAN'S SONG.</songTitle>

<subheading>THE CAPTAIN.</subheading>

<commentary>
"A large portion of that which has passed, 
and is still passing with the Chinese for music to be enjoyed, 
distances barbarian sympathies and defies barbarian analysis. 
Their ideas of music are so at variance with every one of our feelings, 
fancies, practices in art, or ideas of beauty, 
that one can only wonder at them while listening to them ; 
for wonderful it is, that a people so rich and ancient as the Chinese, 
one so advanced in the knowledge of secrets of colour, 
refinement of texture, peculiarity of form ; so skilled in exquisite calligraphy — 
a people to boot who possess a philosophy, 
a fiction, and a drama of their own, all indicating a separate civilization, 
should be so utterly savage and repulsive in their musical tendencies. 
What we know of Chinese melody is in every respect more rude and shapeless than that of far more savage peoples."
</commentary>

<commentary>
Whatever our opinion of Chinese music may be, 
it cannot be less flattering than theirs of ours. 
A very intelligent Chinese, on hearing some music of Rameau's and other French composers, 
hinted politely that it was sadly devoid of meaning and expression, while the music of 
his own country penetrated to the innermost soul.
The common scale of the Chinese consists of only five different intervals. 
The number five appears to be an especially mysterious one with the Chinese. 
I give this almost national tune a place amongst the water melodies, 
as it is a great favourite on sea as well as on land, and it is a fair specimen of Chinese song.
</commentary>

<songTitle str="MOO-LEE-WHA" originLocation="China" subject="sl">CHINESE AIR. ("MOO-LEE-WHA.")</songTitle>

<commentary>
Sir John Barrow gives an English translation of the words of the song "Moo-lee-wha;" 
it is in praise of the flower Moo-lee:
</commentary>

<lyrics>
How delightful this branch of fresh flowers !
One morning, one day, it was dropped in my house.
I, the owner, will wear it not out of doors,
But I will hold the fresh flower and be happy.
How delightful this branch of the Moo-lee flower !
In the full plot of flowers blooming none excels it ;
I, the owner, will wear this gathered branch,
Wear it, yet fear, the flower seen, men will envy.
</lyrics>

<commentary>
As the gondoliers of Venice while away their long midnight hours on the waters with strophes of Tasso, 
the Greek sailors of the Archipelago with fragments of Homer, 
so the trackers in China accompany their severe labour with a song.
</commentary>

<songTitle str="SONG OF CHINESE ROWERS" originLocation="China" subject="sl">SONG OF CHINESE ROWERS.</songTitle>

<subheading>SOLO BY THE MASTER.</subheading>

<lyrics>
Hai - yo hai - yan ! hai - yo, hai - yan !
CHORUS BY THE CREW.
Hai - yo hai - yan !
SOLO BY THE MASTER.
Hai - yo !
Hai - wha de,
Hai - yo, hai - yan !
Hai - yan !
Hai - yo hai - yan !
</lyrics>

<commentary>
On many a still evening, when a dead silence reigned upon the water, 
we have listened with pleasure to the artless and unpolished air, 
which was sung with little alteration through the whole fleet.
</commentary>

<heading id="NEW_ZEALAND">NEW ZEALAND. THE MAORIES.</heading>

<commentary>
It is said of the Maories, in New Zealand, 
that they are so much attached to singing as often to spend the entire night in its gratification, and all work is prosecuted with the aid of song.
Mr. Shortland has collected the words of several of the songs or, more properly speaking, 
chants which are used by the Maories when they are hauling heavy logs of wood or canoes overland, 
in order to ensure a simultaneous
effort of the men engaged in the work. The five lines at the commencement, called Puwha or Hari, are sung by a single voice, 
to prepare the labourers for pulling, and the lines which follow the Puwha are sung alternately, 
solo and tutti, the labourers always responding in chorus to the singing of the leader, and hauling the boat at the same instant all together :
</commentary>

<songTitle str="MAORI HAULING CHANT" originLocation="New Zealand" subject="sl">MAORI HAULING CHANT.</songTitle>
<lyrics>Solo. " Pull, Tainui, pull the Arawa, 
To launch them on the ocean. 
 
Of thunder, falling hitherward, 
On my sacred day. 
 
Chorus. Kiwi. 

Solo. The Moho cries 
Chorus. Moho. 

Solo. The Tieke cries 
Chorus. Tieke. 

Solo. A belly only, 
Chorus. Fork it out, fork it out ! 

Solo. Keep in the path, 
Chorus. Fork it out ! 

It's the second year to-day, 
Cheerily, men ! 
It's the man-catcher, 
Cheerily, men ! 
Give this way, and carry it, 
Cheerily, men ! 
But whither carry it ? 
Cheerily, men ! 
Ah ! to the root, 
Root of Tu. 
Solo. O wind, 
Chorus. Pull away. 

Solo. Pull onwards the root, 
Chorus. Root of Tu." 
Kiwi, Moho, and Tieke are names of birds. </lyrics>

<commentary>The Maories also possess a similar kind of song to the 
natives of the Paumotu group, Polynesia, and those of the 
Sandwich Islands, namely, the Song of Welcome. The 
turtle-fishers of the Fiji Islands have also this Song of 
Welcome when they return from the fisheries. If they 
have been successful, they come shouting songs of triumph, 
and the women come down to the shore to meet them 
also singing, and sometimes as an additional mark of joy 
they pelt a quantity of bitter oranges at their respective 
husbands, sons, and brothers. On the contrary, if they 
have not met with success, they have a sort of chant of the 
most solemn nature which is used.

Respecting the signs employed in the notation of this song, 
which I am quoting from Carl Engel's most valuable 
work on " National Music," it must be observed that J $ is 
meant to raise a note a quarter-tone ; J $ raises it a 
semitone, as does our single sharp ; | # raises it three 
quarter-tones. The same with flats : J t? is meant to lower 
a note a quarter-tone ; and so on. The sign ^ is used to 
indicate that the voice is to glide from one interval to 
another, much as when the finger is drawn over the violin 
string to a certain distance. Mr. Davies, who is responsible 
for the foregoing notation, has made a study of the Maories 
for some twenty years, and may therefore, I think, be re- 

lied upon for authentic information concerning them. He 
pronounces them to be gifted with a remarkably fine ear 
for distinguishing quarter-tones ; they are to be congratu- 
lated on the intelligence, that one would think must be 
characteristic of them, to enable them to become familiar 
with what seems to us such a difficult style of notation ; 
and yet the Maories are as much addicted to cannibalism 
as the natives of the Marquesas Archipelago, with the 
exception, of course, of those who .have come under the 
influence of European civilization and Christianity. 

Every circumstance in the life of a native of New Zealand 
has a song dedicated to the season ; thus in fishing, canoe 
and house-building, planting, sowing, reaping, felling 
timber, paddling canoes, births, marriages, and deaths, 
peace and war, each has its characteristic chant, accom- 
panied by a chorus. The chants are simple, and the 
musical subjects few, but the words embodying the scanty 
musical scores are innumerable. Poetical composition is 
not practised, detached sentences in prose forming the 
groundwork for the music, which are compositions without 
the attempt at finish as among Europeans, yet a step 
nearer to a musical piece than the chant of a recitative can 
be pronounced. 

Many complaints are made of the ill-conduct of the 
American, French, and English seamen at the Bay of 
Islands, but, says Mr. J. S. Polack, in his " Manners and 
Customs of the New Zealanders," " we would inquire of 
those seeming philanthropists, are our ports in Great Britain 
kept wholly immaculate ? And will the Jack Tar of Ports- 
mouth repudiate his lass or his glass, or will the French 
matelot at Nantes or Bordeaux cease his song, and refuse 
to join in quaffing the rich juices afforded by the vintage 
of the Garonne, or will the Yankee sailor of Massachusetts, 
or the Bucksin of ' ole Virginny,' fail less to kick at the 
dispiriting measures of the select, social, temporal teeto- 
talers," who, he avers, would drive all sociability into " an 
eternal everlasting fix." 

Some hundreds of natives are at the present 
moment manning ships sailing under the British, French^ 
and American flags, and are regarded by unbiassed persons 
equal in their duties to European seamen, and as effective 
in ability and strength, while dieting on similar provisions. 
The New Zealand seaman may now be found in every 
part of the globe under the frozen zones of the north and 
south, and the torrid latitudes east and west, steering at 
night and alone on deck the full-freighted ship, amid the 
pathless waters, joining the hilarity of his brother-seamen, 
and equally watchful aloft when danger may approach, and 
may be said to present the nearest approach to a British 
tar beyond any other nation of which we know. </commentary>

<subheading>ICELAND</subheading>
 
<commentary>Mr. Baring Gould, in his volume, "Iceland, its Scenes and 
Sagas," gives one or two specimens of genuine Icelandic 
melody. He says that all the songs were in Icelandic, 
but the melodies were mostly Danish ; " God Save the 
Queen " and " Beautiful Star " were both set to Icelandic 
words, and descriptive of the glories of the island. I give 
the Icelandic National Hymn : 
 
The hymn which follows is one that is frequently used 
by the natives. It is a genuine Icelandic melody : 

The Esquimaux have two sorts of boats or canoes, the 
kia or man's boat, and the oomiak or woman's boat ; this 
latter is the more perfect vessel of the two, as it is often 
used for the transport of more than one person and 
also for the conveyance of luggage. It can scarcely be 
said to be a comfortable vessel though. The women 
paddle their own canoe, but an old man generally steers 
the oomiak. He is selected because of his age, and 
though considered sufficiently able to direct the woman's 
canoe, is supposed to be too old for the kia or man's 
boat. I believe it is no uncommon thing for this old 
Charon to fling a knife, harpoon, or even a seal-hook at 
the ladies if they should neglect their paddling. When I 
read this in Wood's "Natural History of Man," it struck me 
as evidence of a very poor spirit in the fair sex of those 
northern shores, to allow themselves to be so treated by 

one old man amongst perhaps a crew of six or eight 
women in mid-ocean. An Englishman, and certainly not 
an old one, would never be allowed a repetition of 
such amiable gallantry in a boatful of his country- 
women. One attempt at throwing a harpoon or knife 
and he would have laid down his steering-gear for ever, 
and gone to keep company with the fishes.</commentary> 

<heading id="BOAT-SONGS OF THE SAMOAN AND TONGA ISLANDERS"</heading>

<commentary>
A gentleman attached to the United States Exploring Expedition wrote down the following boat-songs of the Samoan or Navigators' Islanders. He says : " The natives, owing to their communication with the Tonga or Friendly Isles, have some knowledge of Captain Cook, and a translation of the first of the boat-songs would run thus :

' Cook tells you, Pull away ;
I will do so, and so must you.'

In their trips from town to town they are generally on parties of pleasure termed Malanga, and are frequently to be met with singing their boat-songs."
</commentary>

<songTitle str="SONGS OF THE SAMOAN ISLANDERS" originLocation="Samoa" subject="sl">SONGS OF THE SAMOAN ISLANDERS.</songTitle>


<lyrics>
Fo-fa . e,

Fo-fa - e.

Na - a- gi-le-fo - e,

Na - a - gi-le.
</lyrics>

<lyrics>
Tu - te ta- ma - i
le fou ane,

Au ta- na - a - lo fi - a - oe,

- te ta - ma - i le fou ane.

Au ta - na - a - lo fi - a - oe.
</lyrics>

<commentary>
The music of the Tonga Islands bears a great resemblance to the Samoan ; 
I have therefore included a few remarks on it. 
The following is a song used by the natives of Tonga-taboo, 
when advancing in a boat with their chief. 
The traveller who noted this song mentions that he wrote it exactly as he heard it, 
with the bass and harmony. It is to be inferred that it is native, for the Tongese never had foreign music of any kind taught.
The Tonga Islanders possess several songs descriptive of historical occurrences. 
One of these is commemorative of the principal events that happened during Captain Cook's visit, 
and which, excepting a little exaggeration, is tolerably—
The Tongese have many short songs, 
which they call Tow Aloy and sing when they are paddling their canoes, 
the strokes of the paddle being coincident with the cadence of the tune. 
They are very frequently sung on leaving Vavaoo, whilst paddling out of the inlet. 
The following is an example of the words and an English translation :
</commentary>

<subheading>ENGLISH VERSION.</subheading>

<lyrics>
Alas ! we are entering upon our—

By leaving Moonga-lafa and Talow !
Anxious am I to stay ; who can wish to go?
Departing from Vavaoo and her neighbouring isles,
And Licoo-one, and Vaoo-aca,
The road of springs near Maccapapa,
Mataloco and the myrtle plain,
The cave of Tootaw-i, the beach of—

No longer can I stand upon high—

And look downwards on the fleet of small canoes.
We must leave the crimson gnatoo of Tlaf6oloohow,
To wear the coarser mats of Toofooa and Kaoo !
</lyrics>

<commentary>
Most of their song-words are in the Samoan language. 
The following is a specimen of the paddling-songs, 
which really form the principal water-music of the Tonga Islands :
</commentary>

<commentary>Rather fast.</commentary>

<songTitle str="TONGESE WATER-SONG" originLocation="Tonga" subject="sl">TONGESE WATER-SONG.</songTitle>

<lyrics>
Oiaooe ! gooa mow teoo felow,
Ca toogoo Moonga-lafa, bea mo Talao !
Gooa te leoli ger nofo ; coliai te"nne aloo?

Ca toogoo Vavaoo, moe motoo lalo,
Licoo o'ne, Moe Vaoo-aca,
Moe Tlalla-vy' gi Maccapapa,
Mattaloco, mo fanga myile,
A'na a Tootaw-i, bea Mofooe,
Iky' Seoo too gi lu lufoanga,
Yio hifo gi he felow ta fanga,
Toogoo he foogi hea a Tlafoolooh6w
Ger vala he gnafi-gnafi a Toofooa mo—
</lyrics>
 
<heading id="THE INDIANS OF NORTH-WEST AMERICA"></heading> 
 
<commentary>Amongst the many and varied kinds of music and song- 
verses that have come under my notice since I entered 
upon the task of collecting the " Music of the Waters," 
there is no specimen of notation that has struck me as 
being so entirely original, and, if I may use the word, so 
comical, as those of the Indians, as described by Max 
Miiller in the chapter devoted to the " Popol Vuk," in the 
first volume of his " Chips from a German Workshop." 
I mean the war-songs and love-songs in the picture- 
writing, and which were really supposed to be perfectly 
intelligible to all the tribes. What should we, enlightened 
mortals of this nineteenth century, make of the following, 
for instance : 

1. Figure representing a god (monedo) endowed with 
magic power. 

2. Figure beating the drum and singing ; lines from his 
 
3. Figure surrounded by a secret lodge. 

4. Two bodies joined with one continuous arm. 

5. A woman on an island. 

6. A woman asleep ; lines from his ear towards her. 

7. A red heart in a circle. 
 
1. It is my form and person that make me great. 

2. Hear the voice of my song, it is my voice. 

3. I shield myself with secret coverings. 

4. All your thoughts are known to me, blush ! 

5. I could draw you hence were you ever so far. 

6. Though you were on the other hemisphere 

7. I speak to your naked heart. 

I can picture the blank amazement of the modern sailor 
if asked to convey his sentiments to " Kate " or " Nancy " 
in some such way, and Nancy's bewilderment if he suc- 
ceeded in so doing; and yet I may almost say, that the 
foregoing is a specimen of an American-Indian sea- 
song, for it was chiefly of the sea and by the sea that 
these tribes lived. Max Miiller adds, " All we can say is, 
that if the Indians can read this writing, they are greater 
adepts in the mysteries of love than the judges of the old 
cours &amp; amour. But it is much more likely that these 
war-songs and love-songs are known to the people 
beforehand, and that their writings are only meant to 
revive what exists in the memory of the reader. It is a 
kind of mnemonic writing, and it has been used by 
missionaries for similar purposes, and with considerable 
 
Captain Dixon gives the notes of the following 
song, which he says he often heard whilst in Norfolk 
Sound : </commentary>



<commentary>The North- American Indians have quite a notion of 
harmony, if one may judge by these specimens of their 
music. Almost all the inhabitants of that part of the 
world have a remarkable capacity for music. The song 
which follows is sung by the traders when nearing a 
strange crew. The chief usually approaches first, singing 
and crossing his arms, as a sign of friendship. </commentary>

<subheading>SONG OF WELCOME OF THE TRADERS.</subheading>
 
<heading id = "NEGRO SONGS OF WESTERN AFRICA"></heading> 

<commentary>" Most negro tribes appear to possess a remarkably keen 
susceptibility for rhythmical regularity. This is evident 
from their dances with the usual accompaniment of drums 
and other instruments of percussion, executed with the 
greatest possible precision. Their songs, however, often 
consist of merely short melodies, which, like the recitative, 
do not possess a strictly defined symmetrical construction. 
The cause of this may be attributed to the circumstance 
that the negroes on many occasions are in the habit of im- 
provising the words of their songs, and that the melodies 
must therefore continually undergo slight modifications 
demanded by the improvised poetry, which, as regards the 
number of the syllables, as well as the metre in general, is 
not always constructed precisely after the same rule, but 
alters according to the momentary inventions of the im- 
provisator." 2 This " Serere " air which follows is a boat- 
song, and is sung by the crew while rowing. It has 
been noticed that the rowing is performed in strict time 
with the song. The letters R above the stave show the 
moment when the oars are raised, and the letters L denote 
their being lowered into the water. This air, therefore, is 
most strictly regular as to rhythm. Whatever may be the 
interior changes from triple to common measure, the time 
which the respective changes consume must be equal, for 
what can be more isochronous than the movement of the 
oars of a well-trained boat's-crew ! Another very rhyth- 
mical air is the following Mandingo one : </commentary>

<heading id = "CREOLE WATER-SONGS"><heading> 

<commentary>Mr. George W. Cable, writing in the Century Magazine, 
April, 1886, on Creole slave-songs, devotes a page to the 
songs of the chase and of the boat. Of these latter he has 
most courteously allowed me to make use. He says " that 
the circumstances which produced these songs have dis- 
appeared. Travelling in Louisiana used only to be by 
water. Every planter had his boat and skilled crew of 
black oarsmen. The throb of their song measured the 
sweep of the oars, and as their bare or turbaned heads and 
shining bodies bowed forward and straightened back in 
ceaseless alternation, their strong voices chanted the praise 
of the silent, broad- hatted master, who sat in the stern. 
Now and then a line would be interjected in manly boast 
of their own brawn, and often the praise of the master 
softened off into tender laudations of the charms of some 
black or tawny Zilie, Zabette, or Zalli" The following 
are a few stanzas of one of the rowing-songs : </commentary>
 
<lyrics>" Sing, lads, our master bids us sing, 

For master cry out loud and strong. 
The water with the long oar strike, 
Sing, lads, and let us haste along. 

" Tis for our master we will sing, 

We'll sing for our young mistresses, 
And sweethearts we must not forget, 
Zoe, Mertente, Zabelle, Louish. 

" Sing, fellows, for our own true loves, 
My lottery prize ! Zoe, my belle ! 
She's like a wild young doe, she knows 
The way to jump and dance so well ! 

" Black diamonds are her bright, black eyes, 

Her teeth are lilies white ; 
Sing, fellows, for my true love, and 
The water with the long oar strike. 

" See ! see the town ! hurrah ! hurrah ! 

Master returns in pleasant mood ; 
He's going to treat his boys all round, 
Hurrah ! hurrah for master good ! " 

Another song quoted is of wood and water, though 
only the latter is mentioned. It is a " Runaway's Song of 
Defiance " : 

" General Florido ! indeed, fo' true dey can't catch me. 
General Florido ! indeed, fo' true dey can't catch me." 

" Dey got one schooner out at sea, 
Dey got one schooner out at sea. 
Indeed, fo' true dey can't catch me."</lyrics></section>


<section id = "SUPERSTITIONS, CUSTOMS, AND WATER- 
LEGENDS OF THE SEA, RIVERS, AND LAKES."> 

<quote>KNOWLEDGE is, of course, to superstition as light is to darkness; still 
some nations endowed with a lively imagination, although they are 
much advanced in mental development, cling to the superstitions of 
their forefathers, since the superstitions accord with their poetical 
conceptions, or are endeared to them by associations which pleasantly 
engage the imaginative faculties. </quote>

<quote>Anon you shall hear a hog grunt, a calf bleat, and an ass bray, 
Because it is Saint Peter's holiday." 

MARLOWE'S Faustus.</quote> 

<quote>' Bird whom I welcomed while the sailors cursed." 

THEODORE WATTS' Ode to Mother Carey's Chicken.</quote> 

<heading id = "SAILORS' SUPERSTITIONS"></heading> 

<commentary>" A COMPARATIVE investigation of the superstitions rife 
amongst the different sailors of the world would result in 
a certain conclusion that there is but little variety in them. 
Certain objects, certain signs, and certain persons inspire 
Jack with an idea of the supernatural, whether European, 
Asiatic, or American. The Portsmouth tar, the Normandy 
matelot, the German seaman, and the Italian fisherman, 
all share in common with the Nile boatman, the Chinese 
waterman, and the Yankee blue-jacket, the fears that have 
been handed down from their respective marine ancestors 
for generations. Sailors, although usually the bravest 
men, have from time immemorial been noted for their 
credulity, and every literature contains evidence of the 
multiplicity of their superstitions, and of the tenacity with 
which they cling to them. It may be questioned, how- 
ever, whether as a class they are really more superstitious 
than landsmen, the only difference perhaps being that their 
isolation, consequent from their connection with the sea, 
gives them a distinctive character, which otherwise they 
would not possess. Their history, too, dating from the 
most remote period in the annals of the world, has natu- 
rally invested them with a peculiar interest in this and 
other countries. And hence we find scattered here and 
there many a curious account recorded by travellers of 
their customs and peculiarities, to give a detailed resume 
of which would occupy a volume of considerable size. 
Indeed, as Reginald Scott has truly remarked in his 
' Discovery of Witchcraft,' innumerable are the reports of 

accidents unto such as frequent the seas as fishermen and 
sailors, who discourse of noises, flashes, shadows, echoes, 
and other visible appearances nightly seen and heard upon 
the surface of the water." 1 

Amongst the animals which the sailor considers as 
omens of good or ill-luck are cats, hares, rats, porpoises, 
or sea-hogs. Certain birds also come under this category, 
the Stormy Petrel, the great auk, the kingfisher, and the 
 
The cat is the object of many an odd belief. In the 
neighbourhood of Scarborough, for instance, we are told 
how a few years ago sailors' wives were in the habit of 
keeping black cats to ensure the safety of their husbands 
at sea ; black cats thus increased in value to such an extent, 
that few could afford the luxury of them. Many sailors 
object to having cats on board, and if one happens to be 
more frisky than usual, they have a saying that " the cat 
has got a gale of wind in her tail." Also a firm notion 
exists amongst seamen, that the throwing of a cat over- 
board will bring on a storm. A dead hare on board a ship is 
considered a sign of an approaching hurricane, and Cornish 
fishermen (than whom no more superstitious set of men 
exist) declare that a white hare seen about the quays at 
night indicates that there will be rough weather. The 
fisherman of Filey, like the Japanese sailor, hesitates to go 
to sea on any day when he has encountered a pig early in 
the morning. The blue-jackets of the " Empire of the 
Rising Sun," however, have an equal objection to meeting 
a priest previous to setting out upon a voyage. Piggie is 
an object of aversion to more seafaring people than the 
Filey fishermen and Japanese sailors ; there is scarcely a 
book or article on the superstitions of the sea that I have 
read, that does not allude to his Jonah-like propensities. 
As to rats, we all well know of their connection with 
ships. Shakespeare, in the most nautical of his plays, 
( The Tempest," says, in speaking of the vessel in which 
1 Extract from the Leisure Hour. 

Prospero and Miranda had been placed with a view to their 
destruction : </commentary>

<quote>" The very rats 
Instinctively had quit it."</quote> 

<commentary>It is said that rats leave a ship in harbour, previous to 
its being lost at sea. Sometimes there is a reason for this 
sudden desertion, as in the case of the cunning Welsh 
captain whose ship was infested with them. He was lying 
in the Mersey, and learning that there was a vessel laden 
with cheese in the basin, he drew alongside of her at dusk, 
left all his hatches open, and when the rats were safely on 
board of that to them Eldorado cheese-laden ship, he 
moved off. 

With regard to birds the Stormy Petrel, as- its name 
betokens, presages bad weather ; the great auk never 
wanders beyond soundings, and thus taking their clue 
from him the sailors know that land is not far off. Of the 
kingfisher it used to be said, that whilst this bird was 
hatching her eggs, the sea remained so calm that the period 
became known as the halcyon days. The Scotch say of 
the sea-gulls :</commentary> 

<quote>" Sea-gull, sea-gull, sit on the sand, 
It's never good weather when you're on the land"</quote> 

<commentary>Bad weather may always be looked for whenever these 
birds leave the open sea and hover near the shore. The 
sea-legends and superstitions that have to do with birds 
are of very ancient date. Aristophanes tells us how the 
Greek sailors heeded their signs :</commentary> 

<quote>" From birds, in sailing, men instructions take, 
Now lie in port, now sail, and profit make."</quote> 

<commentary>The intense dread which sailors and fishermen have of 
the dead is a wide-spread one amongst all nations, and 
the horror of the Chinese sailor, when asked to carry a 
corpse on board, is shared by bis brother blue-jackets on 
every sea ; they say the sea cannot digest the crudity of a 

dead body, it being a due debt to be interred where it 
lieth, and a ship cannot abide to be made a bier of. 

" On certain parts of the coast in Cornwall, sailors dread 
walking at night near those portions of the shore where 
there have been many wrecks, for they firmly believe that 
the souls of drowned sailors haunt such localities, and 
further affirm that the calling of the dead has frequently 
been heard. Indeed at night-time, on the approach of a 
tempest, these callings are declared to be of common occur- 
rence, and many a sailor positively asserts that he has heard 
the voices of the dead sailors * hailing their own names.' " l 

Friday is considered by the sailors as an unlucky day 
to set sail upon or begin any work. One cannot wonder 
at the prevalence of this idea amongst them, seeing how 
deeply-rooted it has become amongst all classes and 
nations ; but we may query the wisdom of a sneeze to 
the left or the right side, at the moment of embarking, 
having any effect upon the voyage being favourable or 
otherwise. It is also considered very unlucky if any one 
accidentally numbers the sailors on board, or to ask Scotch 
sailors or fishermen before they start on a journey where 
they are bound for ! And to point with the finger to a 
ship when at sea is most disastrous ; the whole hand 
should be raised up to counteract the evil consequences. 
It is a bad sign if a water-bucket or a mop is lost, and no 
one must cut his hair or nails at sea, except during a 
storm ; thus a calm voyage would return a crew whose 
fingers would be formidable weapons to encounter, and 
whose locks would be suggestive of Rip Van Winkle or 
Robinson Crusoe. 

Whistling is thought very unlucky by sailors, as it is 
supposed to raise an unfavourable wind. This superstition 
is, I fancy, to be traced to the practice of whistling for 
winds, common to many nations in days gone by, which 
used to exist, and which I have elsewhere mentioned. A 
whistling woman is a bete noire to Jack. 

The moon and clouds also play an important part in a 
sailor's life, and the notion that the weather changes with 
the moon's quarters is firmly implanted in them.</commentary>

<lyrics>" I saw the new moon late yester-e'en, 
With the old moon in her arm ; 
And if we go to sea, master, 
I fear we'll come to harm."</lyrics> 

<commentary>This used to be a favourite rhyme in the sixteenth 
 
Seamen find it convenient to express many important 
facts in rhymes, and a few of the more prominent are here 
given : </commentary>

<lyrics>" The evening gray and morning red, 
Put on your hat or you'll wet your head." 

" When the wind shifts against the sun, 
Trust it not, for it will run." 

" When the sun sets in the clear, 
An easterly wind you need not fear." 

" The evening red and morning gray, 
Are sure signs of a fine day ; 

But the evening gray and morning red 
Make the sailor shake his head."</lyrics> 

<commentary>Adverting to the barometer :</commentary> 

<lyrics>"First rise, after low, 

Indicates a stronger blow." </lyrics>
 
<lyrics>" Long foretold, long last ; 
Short notice, soon past." </lyrics>

<commentary>To which may be added : </commentary>

<lyrics>" In squalls, 

When the rain's before the wind, 
Halyards, sheets, and braces mind." 
 
" When the wind's before the rain, 
Soon you may make sail again." </lyrics>

<commentary>Also speaking generally :</commentary> 

<lyrics>" When the glass falls low 
Prepare for a blow, 
 
Let all your kites fly." 

" A rainbow in the morning, 
Sailors take warning ; 
 
Is the sailors' delight."</lyrics> 

<commentary>In fact there is no end to the superstitions that exist, or 
perhaps I should say, existed among sailors ; indeed, after 
searching through the works which treat of these, one 
almost wonders at the light-heartedness characteristic of 
the blue-jackets when one thinks of the burden laid upon 
them through them. </commentary>

<heading id = "RELIGIOUS CEREMONIES"></heading> 

<commentary>The fishermen of Clovelly were formerly in the habit of 
inaugurating the commencement of the herring-fishing 
season by attending a special service at the church ; 
the I07th Psalm being substituted for the Psalm of the 
day, and the gospel of the fifth Sunday after Trinity 
being read on the occasion. The old Hundredth Psalm, 
too, was sung by all the fishermen before the general 
thanksgiving, and after it came that unique prayer known 
as the Clovelly Fishermen's Prayer, which begins "Al- 
mighty and loving Father, Thou rulest in the heaven, in 
the earth, in the sea, and in all deep places." The Clovelly 
fishermen's example is not often followed ; there are 
many places where, like the herring-fishers of Marken 
(Holland), the little flotilla sails on a Sunday evening. 

Many of the fishing community are of a decidedly 
religious character, thus following the example of their 
patron saint, St. Peter. Oftentimes on a summer's evening, 
off the Cornish coast, one may hear the fishermen engaged 
in singing hymns of praise. Like the Dutch seafaring 
men, these Cornish men are most fervent in their devotions ; 
the rugged, lonely, perilous lives they lead being responsible 
for the solemnity of their bearing/The Breton and 
Norman fishermen are also very God-fearing people. 

The herring fishery in the Isle of Man is the staple 
industry of the place the Manx sea-harvest it is called. 
Before the men set off for the fishing a service is held, and 
to the verse in the Church Litany, " That it may please 
Thee to give and preserve to our use the kindly fruits 
of the earth, so as in due time we may enjoy them," is 
added, "and restore and continue to us the blessings of 
the sea." Bishop Wilson had this supplemented in the 
Manx Book of Common Prayer, in 1779. Also, before 
shooting the nets, at a sign from the master of the boat, 
every man goes down upon his knees, and with his head 
uncovered asks that a blessing may be upon the fishing. 
They are a thoroughly devout people, these silent, earnest, 
shrewd Manx fishermen, and there is a great deal to interest 
one in their sayings and doings. For instance, a Manx 
fisherman counts 124 fish to the hundred, he adds three to 
every hundred (120) which he distinguishes by the name 
of " warp," and then he throws in a single herring which 
he calls " tally," thus making 124. They have some queer 
proverbs about herrings. They are delicate fish and very 
easily killed ; when they are taken out of the water they 
give a peculiar squeak, and die thus, " As dead as a 
herring " is a favourite saying, and as they are caught by 
the gills in the meshes of the net, with all their heads 
hanging in the same direction, " Every herring must hang 
by his own gill." Like the Zetland fishermen, the Manx 
have a toast, " Life to man and death to fish " (Manx) 
" Bioys da dooinne as baase da eeast." 

A belief in the supernatural is strongly rooted in the 
minds of the sea-going community ; amongst necromantic 
agencies, bells occupy a very prominent place. Occasion- 
ally, during a hurricane, the death-bell is clearly heard 
borne along the angry billows ; a superstition alluded to 
by Sir Walter Scott : </commentary>

<quote>" And the belfrie rang, 
And the sea-maid sang, 
The dirge of lovely Rosabelle." </quote>

<commentary>Southey, in his famous ballad of the " Inchcape Bell," has 
immortalized one of these bell legends. Once on the 
sands near Blackpool, out at sea, stood the church of 
Kilgrimal, now completely submerged ; wanderers near this 
spot, however, are still said from time to time to be terri- 
fied by the dismal chimes of the bells as they send forth 
their doleful peals over the murmuring sea. The people 
of Pembroke, too, hear a sunken bell ring from its watery 
grave when a storm is rising. It is supposed to be the 
great bell of St. David's, Pembrokeshire, which was carried 
off during the Cromwellian wars ; the robbers managed to 
get it on board ship, but in passing through Ramsey Sound 
the vessel was wrecked a direct result, the superstitious 
said, of profanely treating the bell. Denmark has many of 
these legends. There is one at Gossingen about two bells 
which were ordered to be cast in the town of Lubeck. 
These bells were brought by sea to Schleimunde ; but, as 
ill-luck would have it, one of them fell into the sea and 
was lost. From that day, whenever the remaining bell is 
being rung, it distinctly proclaims " My companion lies in 
the Schleimunde." 

During tempests at Malta it is usual to ring all the bells 
in the Roman Catholic churches for an hour, that the 
wind may cease and the sea be calmed. This custom also 
prevails in Sicily and Sardinia. There is a Cornish legend 
that the bells of Bottreaux church were sent by ship, but 
when the vessel was in sight of the town, the blasphemy 
 
of the captain was punished by the loss of his ship. The 
bells are supposed to lie in the bay and announce by 
strange sounds the approach of a storm. 

The late Henry Smart has set to music the legend of the 
town of" Vineta," on the Baltic once, it is said, the greatest 
emporium in the north of Europe several times destroyed 
and built up again, till in 1183, it was upheaved by an 
earthquake and swallowed by a flood. The ruins of Vineta 
are popularly believed to be visible on certain days, and 
their bells audible below the waves, between the coast of 
Pomerania and the island of Rugen. By the kind permis- 
sion of Messrs. Novello, Ewer, and Co., I am enabled to 
give the air of this most beautiful song, and the words 
which are from the Schleswig-Holstein poetry : </commentary>

<lyrics>From the sea's deep hoi- low faint - ly peal 

Far - off ev - 'ning bells come sad and slow ;. 

Faint T ly rise, the won- drous tale re - veal - ing 

Of the old en-chant-ed town be - low. On the  
 
bo som of the flood re clin ing, Ruin - ed 

arch and wall and bro - ken spire, Down be 

flash in flakes of gold - en fire 

" And the boatman who at twilight hour . . . 

Once that magic vision shall have seen, 
Heedless how the crags may round him lour, 
Ever more will haunt the charmed scene. 

" From the heart's deep hollow faintly pealing, 

Far I hear those bell -notes sad and slow, 
Ah ! a wild and wond'rous tale revealing 

Of the drowned wreck of love below. 
There a world in loveliness decaying, 

Lingers yet in beauty ere it die ; 
Phantom forms across my senses playing, 

Flash like golden fire-flakes from the sky. 
Lights are gleaming, fairy bells are ringing, 

And I long to plunge and wander free, 
Where I hear the angel voices singing 

In those ancient towers below the sea, 

In those ancient towers below the sea."</lyrics> 

<heading>MUSICAL SOUNDS AND FISH<heading> 

<commentary>An Italian savant has discovered a new and simple 
method of catching fish ; the bait is a musical one. The 
Gazetta del Popolo says, "As we all know, the sense of 
hearing is extraordinarily developed in fish ; it appears that 
while the slightest noise scatters them in all directions, a 
musical note, especially that produced by the human voice, 
attracts them ; on hearing it they stop suddenly in their 
course. Signer Saretti discovering this fact, embarked one 
morning on the Lake of Geneva with a party of friends. 
He possesses a very fine deep bass voice, and striking up a 

national song he proved to his astonished companions the 
truth of his assertions. They were able by means of an 
aquascope to perceive the eagerness with which the 
piscine population gathered around the little boat. Casting 
over the nets they had brought, they instantly made such 
a catch as has rarely, if ever, been known on the lake, and 
they may be said indeed to have made another miraculous 
draught of fishes." 

Fish again are charged with being voiceless, but how 
then about the gurnard that pipes, the diodon that grunts, 
and the others that drum and whistle and play on Jew's 
harps ? The legend that they were caught in Egypt by 
singing to them is not without its plausibility. " Fishes, 
though little, have very long ears " is an old Chinese 
proverb ; and to this day, on the Danube, men hang little 
bells to their nets to attract fish. In Japan the same fish 
are summoned to dinner by melodious gongs. In India 
we have seen them called up out of the muddy depths 
of the river at Dholpore by the ringing of a handbell J 
and from the abbey in Belgium, where the carp answer 
at once to the whistle of the monks who feed them, right 
away to Otaheite, where the chiefs have pet eels which 
they whistle to the surface, the same belief in the sym- 
pathy of fish with musical sounds will on inquiry be found 
prevailing. "Dull as a mullet" was a Roman proverb, 
yet the very men who quoted it, prided themselves on the 
docility, sensitiveness to sound, and personal attachment 
of their favourite mullets. We are inclined, therefore, to 
think that the finned folk have been somewhat calum- 
niated ; a grudge, it is possible, has been borne against the 
fish, under the idea that they escaped the deluge. 

In Chamber Journal (July 3rd, 1886) there appeared 
a very interesting article entitled " Musical Sand." The 
existence of musical or sonorous sand is not much known, 
although such sand appears to occur in localities widely 
distributed over the earth's surface. There is the so-called 
" Singing Beach " at Manchester-by-the-Sea, Massachusetts, 

and a beach of sonorous sand at Eigg, and also in the 
 
Specimens of sonorous sand are to be found in the 
island of Bornholm, Denmark ; Colberg, Prussia ; and 
Kanai, Hawaii Islands. Old Chinese chronicles mention 
sonorous sand as occurring in the desert of Lob-Nor. 
Marco Polo narrates superstitions concerning it, and the 
Emperor Baber refers to a locality in Afghanistan where 
it is found. Careful search in literature shows that allusions 
to this phenomenon are scattered sparingly through writ- 
ings of a thousand years. 

The character of the sounds obtained by friction on the 
beach is decidedly musical. The shrillness and lowness of 
note depend chiefly on the quantity of sand disturbed. By 
plunging both hands into the sand and bringing them 
together quickly, a tone is heard, the dominant note of 
which is B below the treble stave. By stroking the sand 
nearer the surface and with less force, very high notes were 
heard confused ; they ranged from E, fourth space treble 
clef, to B above the stave. By rubbing firmly and briskly 
a double handful of the sand, several notes on a rising scale 
were heard. The ear received an impression something 
like that formed by sliding a finger up a violin-string at 
the same time that the bow is drawn. 

Sonorous and mute sand occur in the beach closely ad- 
joining, but they cannot be distinguished by the eye ; 
friction alone determines the difference. 

The phenomenon is well worthy of investigation, and no 
light seems as yet to have been thrown on its cause, nor 
any progress made towards the solution of the mystery of 
the difference between mute and musical sand.</commentary> 

<lyrics>" Now lay thine ear against this golden sand, 
And thou shalt hear the music of the sea, 
Those hollow tunes it p!ays against the land, 
Is't not a rich and wondrous melody ? 
I have lain hours, and fancied in its tone 
I heard the languages of ages gone."</lyrics> 

<heading id = "ROMANCES OF THE MERMAIDS"></heading> 

<quote>"The sighs that from thy seamen pass 

Might set a fleet a-sail ; 

And the faces that look in the mermaid's glass 
Are as long as the mermaid's tail." 

RICHARD GARNETT.</quote>

<subheading>MORVA OR MORVETH (SEA-DAUGHTERS).<subheading> 

<commentary>The intimate connection between the inhabitants of 
Brittany, of Cornwall, and of Wales, would appear to lead 
to the conclusion that the Breton word Morverch, or mer- 
maid, had much to do with the naming of the Cornish 
parish of Morva (signifying Locus maritimus, a place near 
the sea). The church of Morva, like most of the churches 
on the coast of Cornwall, was built by and for fishermen, to 
whom the superstitions of mermen and " merry-maids " 
had the familiarity of a creed. 

Whether the mermaids belong to the ^Egean Sea, or the 
Mediterranean, the Pacific, or the Atlantic, we may rest as- 
sured their mission is ever the same to lure to destruction, 
by the marvellous beauty of their persons, and by the 
bewitching songs " plaintive as the waves." Mermaids are 
but rarely considered as benefactors. Legends and tales 
of them generally associate them with some catastrophe. 

Mr. Robert Hunt, in his " Popular Romances of the West 
of England ; or, the Drolls, Traditions, and Superstitions of 
old Cornwall," devotes a chapter to tales of the Cornish 
mermaids ; there is one, " The Mermaid's Rock," which I 
quote, as it is very short, very much to the point, and 
certainly may be taken as a type of mermaid romance in 
general : 

" To the westward of the beautiful Cove of Lemorna is a 
rock which has through all time borne the above name. 
There exists the popular fancy of a lady showing herself 
here previous to a storm with, of course, the invariable 
comb and glass. She is said to have been heard singing 

most plaintively before a wreck, and that, all along the 
shore, the spirits have echoed her in low moaning voices. 
Young men are said to have swam off to the rock, lured by 
the songs which they heard, but they have never returned" 
a peculiarity of young men who endeavour to prosecute 
their acquaintance with mermaids further than viewing 
them from a safe and enchanted distance. Appended to 
this little story in Mr. Hunt's volume, there is a note of 
explanation, which says, " The undulations of the air, 
travelling with more rapidity than the currents, reach our 
shores long before the tempest by which they have been 
established in the centre of the Atlantic, and by producing 
a low moaning sound, * the soughing of the wind,' predi- 
cates the storms." 

There is a longer tale, entitled " The Mermaid's Venge- 
ance," in the same chapter, which introduces several songs ; 
one is sung by the heroine, evidently a very cruel mermaid, 
to the hero, Walter by name, whom she holds by the hair 
of his head :</commentary> 

<lyrics>" Come away, come away 
O'er the waters wild. 
 
Died this day, died this day. 

Come away, come away 
  
For him who did betray. 

Come away, come away 
  
Of him we slay, him we slay. 

Come away, come away 
 
In earth's own breast, 

For many a day, many a day. 

Come away, come away 
 
From coast to coast, 
 
His corse shall float, 

Around the bay, around the bay." </lyrics>

<commentary>That their coiffure is a matter of great we might almost 
say, paramount importance to these water-fairies one can- 
not doubt ; the faithful chronicler of their doings would as 
soon think of representing a soldier without his sword, or 
a fish without a tail, as a mermaid minus her comb and 
glass. Amongst the English sailors' songs, I have men- 
tioned one known as " The Mermaid ;" it is a very 
humorous description of the direful fate of a young sailor 
who fell in with one, and who was doomed to pass the 
rest of his days with this green-haired beauty "at the 
bottom of the deep blue sea." 
 
The necks or water-spirits are renowned for their love 
and talent for music. There exist, people say, various 
kinds of these interesting creatures. The Swedes relate 
wonderful stories respecting the marvellous harp-playing 
of a neck called Stromkarl, who generally prefers the 
vicinity of water-mills and cascades for his abode. 

The neck or nicker has become quite a stranger in 
England. Some Englishmen, however, take care to pre- 
serve his name, applying it to a spirit of another element 
than water, and every one knows at once whom they mean 
when they speak of Old Nick. Like the sirens and the 
mermaids, the female neck enchants youths with sweet 
music, and draws them down into the water. In the Greek 
mythology, Hylas, a king's son, is commemorated as 
having been drawn into the water by nymphs enamoured 
of the beautiful youth. 

The Scandinavian god, Odin, the originator of magic 

songs, is mentioned as the ruler of the sea, and as such he 
had the name of Nikarr. In the depth of the sea he 
played the harp with his subordinate spirits, who occasion- 
ally came up to the surface of the water to teach some 
favourite mortal their wonderful instrument. 

It is a suggestive fact that several nations in different 
parts of the world possess an ancient tradition, according 
to which some harp-like instrument was originally derived 
from the water. 

Another Scandinavian water- deity was Herta, or the 
Storm-compeller, according to tradition, a goddess who 
presided over storms. </commentary>

<lyrics>" What can be more sweet to see 
Than the sailor's agony ? 
While around the wild waves roar, 
And lash with furious rage the shore." </lyrics>

<commentary>The Drottwich canal (Worcestershire), in passing through 
Salwarpe, is said to have cut off a slice of a large, old, half- 
timbered structure, supposed to have been formerly a 
mansion-house; and in revenge for this act of mutilation, 
the ghost of a former occupier revisits his old haunts, 
affrights the domestics, and may be seen on dark nights, 
with deprecatory aspect, to glide down the embankment 
and suicidally commit himself to the waters below. 

" The changes which have taken place in the sea-life 
cannot be wholly restricted to the transformations of the 
ship-building yard. There is a mighty difference, indeed, 
between the line-of-battle ship of fifty years ago and the 
armour-clad of to-day between the Atlantic passenger 
clippers of which Fennimore Cooper wrote and the iron 
mail-steamers which have succeeded them ; but there are 
changes in other maritime directions fully as remarkable, 
though, perhaps, not so deeply accentuated to the shore 
gaze. Where are the old customs of the ocean ? Whither 
has fled the traditionary character of the sailor ? His 
canvas remains ; he still has his topsails, albeit halved, 

to hoist, his topgallant-sails to sheet home, his royals to 
set ; spite of steam, there are still scores of the old-fashioned 
windlasses for him to carol his hurricane songs over ; still 
scores of the old-fashioned capstans to twist round, ' drunk, 
monotonous, and melodious ; ' davits at which he may 
cast his anchor, as did his forefathers ; forecastles as clammy 
as the most reeking of the holes in which the Jacks of 
other days lay snoring, with purple faces, in clouds of cock- 
roaches. But, for all that, it will not do to pretend that 
the sailor is what he was. I do not speak of the carica- 
tures of the fictionist the monstrous pigtailed figures with 
lanthorn jaws, broken teeth, wooden legs, and bloodshot 
eyes ; the race of Hatchways, Trunnions, and Pipses, who 
stagger, full of drink and * language/ in dismal procession 
through the pages of the sea-novelists, losing, to be sure, 
something of their inexpressible garnishing as they enter 
the truer oceanic atmosphere of the Coopers and the 
Marryats of the present century. I refer simply to the old 
sailor, to the plain man-o'-war's man and merchantman of 
bygone years, not to the Frankenstein in flowing breeches 
and hat on nine hairs, who trod the stage and procured his 
circulation in one, two, and three volumes, in the respect- 
able name of Jack, prior even to the days when Sir Lancelot 
Greaves found the irresponsible anatomy willing to ship </commentary>

<quote>" ' The broad habergeon, 
Vant brace and greves and gauntlet.' </quote>

<commentary>Let me be understood. The British or American mariner 
of to-day is as hearty, nimble, dexterous, determined 
a fellow as ever he was at any time during the choicest 
and most glorious period of his nation's history. He 
needs but opportunity to test him. It is in his tradi- 
tions, habits, superstitions, that he differs from his pre- 
decessors. I do not think it is the iron of his latter-day 
calling that has entered his soul and changed him ; the 
very distinguishable difference is owing to a natural decay 
of marine sentiment. He is no longer superstitious 

possibly because he is not without a tincture of education. 
Hard wear has attenuated his prejudices, and custom has 
lost its hold upon him. It would be difficult now, I should 
think, to find in any forecastle such a superstitious sea-dog 
as the old salt who, in Dana's ' Two Years before the 
Mast/ agreed with the black cook as to the malignant 
and wizard qualities of the Finns. Familiarity with the 
grand liquid amphitheatre into which he descends and toils 
for his bread may have helped to rob the modern sailor of 
what I must call the romantic features of the seaman's 
nature. In olden times the voyage was long, the art of 
navigation crude and halting, the wonders of the deep 
were many, at least, they were found so ; a man passed so 
long a while at sea that he was saturated with the spirit of 
it. Superstitions, salt as the billow from which they were 
wrought, begot peculiar forms of thought ; customs grew 
out of the strange fancies and interpretations, and that they 
should now be dead means simply that they flourished for 
centuries, and that they died very hard at last. How wide 
the difference is between the shipboard life of the mariners 
of the past and that of the present race of seamen may be 
collected by looking into a few of the customs which are 
now as extinct as the timbers of Noah's ark. In the seven- 
teenth and eighteenth centuries it was a practice on board 
Italian and Spanish, and possibly Portuguese ships, for 
the sailors, on crossing the equator, to erect a canopy on 
the forecastle, under which three seamen, absurdly dressed, 
seated themselves. One was called the president, the 
others judges. They started first with trying the captain, 
then the officers, and finally the passengers. A sailor, 
dressed up as a clerk, read the indictments, after which the 
judges pronounced sentence of death. Careri, in his 
' Voyage round the World,' explains the purpose of this 
tomfoolery. ' The sentence of death,' says he, 'was imme- 
diately bought off with money, chocolate, sugar, biscuit, 
flesh, sweetmeats, wine, and the like.' The best of it was 
that he who did not pay immediately, or give good security, 

was laid on with a rope's end, at the least sign given by 
the ' President Tarpaulin.' Apparently heavier punish- 
ments than rope's-ending attended the poverty or contumacy 
of the convicted, for the same author tells of a passenger 
who was drowned on board a galleon through being keel- 
hauled for refusing to conform to this singular marine 
custom. The sport if sport it can be called lasted all 
day, and then at sundown the fines or forfeits were divided 
among the sailors. It is possible that out of this old sea 
joke rose the stupid and irritating practice of ducking men 
on their crossing the equator for the first time. This 
imbecile piece of horse-play was wonderfully popular among 
seamen down to quite recent days. I do not think Jack 
ever saw much humour himself in the mere dressing-up as 
Neptune, and acting Jack Pudding in the waist ; what he 
relished was the privilege, by prescription, of lording it over 
the captain and officers for a few hours, and tarring and 
soaking people to whom, at other times, he would have to 
pull his forelock, with the whole length of the ship between 
him and their nobility. Another curious custom was to 
be found on board Dutch vessels. When a ship entered 
the 39th parallel, ' every one,' writes John Nieuhoff (1640), 
* of what quality or degree soever, that has not passed there 
before is obliged to be baptized or redeem himself from it. 
He that is to be baptized has a rope tied round his middle, 
wherewith he is drawn up to the very top of the bowsprit, 
and from thence three times successively tumbled into the 
water. A man was at liberty to get another to take his 
place by paying him.' Plenty of money and other good 
things must have been earned by the sailors out of this 
custom, for one may conceive that a nervous passenger 
would pay handsomely to escape so formidable a ducking 
as the tall bowsprits of those days promised, whilst, on the 
other hand, a seasoned manner would look upon such 
sousings as mere child's play think no more of it than a 
man in a regatta now thinks of walking out upon a greasy 
boom to loose the pig in the sack at the end of it. The 

practice, however, eventually led to such riots, broils, and 
bloodshed, that it was forbidden by the Dutch Government. 
It was long preserved, however, in the British navy as a 
punishment. In the Annual Register for 1797, there is 
an account of four naval officers who were soused by a 
mutinous crew on board his Britannic Majesty's ship 
Sandwich. The writer calls it a 'curious ceremony.' 
The unhappy naval officers must have thought it so ! 

" They tie the unfortunate victims' feet together, and 
their hands together, and put their bed at their back, 
making it fast round them, at the same time adding an 
eighteen-pound ball-shot to bring them down. They 
afterwards make them fast to a tackle suspended from the 
yardarm, and hoisting them nearly up to the block, all at 
once let go, and drop them souse into the sea, where they 
remain a minute, and then are again hoisted and let down 
alternately, till there are scarce any signs of life remaining.' 
When the miserable victims are ducked enough (according 
to the fancy of their judges), they are triced up by the 
heels that the water may run out of them, and then stowed 
away in their hammocks. This kindness was denied to the 
four naval officers, who, after having hung head down for 
some time, were tumbled into a boat and sent ashore." * 

The following extract is from "A Land-Lubber's Log/' 
in the Newcastle Weekly Chronicle : </commentary>

BURYING THE DEAD HORSE. 

<lyrics>Auctioneer. " A poor old man came riding by. 

Chorus. And they say so, and they hope so. 
A uctioneer. A poor old man came riding by. 
Chorus. A poor old man, 

A poor old man came riding by. 
Auctioneer. They say, old man, your horse will die. 
If he dies I will tan his hide, 
And if he lives I will ride him again ; 
I'll have his hide to make my shoes. 

1 Clarke Russell. 

Auctioneer. We'll drag him along to his burial-place, 
O pull, my boys, and make a noise. 
You, poor old horse, what brought you here, 
After carrying turf for many a year 
From Bantry Bay to Ballyack, 
When you fell down and broke your back ? 
You died from blows and sore abuse, 
And were salted down for the sailor's use. 
The sailors they the meat despise, 
They turned you over and (ahem'd) your eyes, 
They ate the meat and picked the bones, 
And gave the rest to Davy Jones ; 
And if you don't believe it's true, 
Go look in the harness cask, and find his shoes.</lyrics>
 
<commentary>" The music to this extraordinary song," says the writer, 
" was strange and crude, but marked by a weird, mournful 
melody, recalling what one has read of the caoine that was 
formerly sung by the Irish over their dead. . . . Each line 
was sung twice over by the auctioneer, and the crew 
followed in chorus with the alternate refrain." The cere- 
mony of " Burying the Dead Horse " is now almost an 
obsolete one, and is rarely witnessed save on Australian- 
bound passenger-ships. As to its origin I cannot find any 
authentic information, the custom is certainly confined to 
the British mercantile service. " The Dead Horse " is 
typical of one month's pay advanced on shore, and which, 
after twenty-eight days, has been worked out. The horse's 
body is made out of a barrel, and his extremities of hay or 
straw, covered with canvas, the mane and tail of hemp, or 
still better, of manilla ; the eyes consist of two ginger-beer 
bottles, which are sometimes filled with phosphorus. 
When the horse is completed, he is lashed to a box, which 
is covered by a rug and then drawn along, in Egyptian 
fashion, on a grating. 

A very humorous description of this ceremony, and 

another set of lines and music known as " The Dead 
Horse," I had sent me, in a copy of The Parramatta Sun 
(a serio-comic magazine, issued fortnightly, during the 
voyage of the ship Parramatta from London to Sydney, 
September 9th, 1879, to December 8th, 1879). </commentary>

<subheading>BURYING THE DEAD HORSE.</subheading>

<commentary>" On Thursday, October 2nd, lat. 7-32 N., long. 25-20 W., 
Mr. Richard Tangye, the well-known judge and buyer of 
blood stock, attended the Parramatta sale, and purchased 
the animal which was too celebrated to need mention by 
name. At about eight o'clock a vast multitude of those 
interested in the turf were assembled on the poop, anxiously 
waiting to catch a glimpse of the noble animal as he 
emerged from his stable in the fore part of the ship. His 
jockey having mounted him, proceeded to the main-deck 
amidst a crowd of the ship's crew, singing as they did a song 
which would have deterred anybody with less spirit than 
Mr. Tangye from bidding. It appeared that the horse was 
a victim to fate, and that his dirge was being sung : </commentary>

<lyrics>" Oh ! now poor horse your time is come, 
And we say so, for we know so. 
Oh ! many a race I know you've won : 
Poor old man. 

2. I have come a long, long way, 

And,

To be sold upon this day. 
Oh, poor old man. 

3. I have made Fordham's heart jump with joy, 

And, 
For many a long time he tried a Derby to win, 

4. But I was the moke to carry him in. 
So I hope I shall fetch plenty of tin. 

5. Oh ! gentlemen, walk up and speculate; 
If I go cheap, my heart will break. 
6. So now, Mr. Auctioneer, you can begin. 

And, 

" Put up, therefore, he was before the poop, the auctioneer 
introducing him to the public by narrating his past and 
prosperous career, and quickly inducing them to make 
spirited bids. The bidding commenced at five shillings, 
and speedily ran up to six pounds ten shillings, each 
person being answerable for the amount of his or her bid. 
The horse and jockey being knocked down, the crew sang 
the following requiem, the melody being the same as that 
for the dirge : 

" Now, old horse, your time is come, 

And we say so, for we know so. 
Altho' many a race you have won. 

Oh, poor old man. 
2. You're going now to say good-bye, 

And,

Poor old horse you're going to die. 
Oh, 

" The procession moving forward, the horse and jockey 
were attached to a rope and hauled up to the main-yardarm, 
and were then, amid plenty of blue fire (stay, the jockey, 
who happened to be alive, was spared) committed to the 
deep. The crew then sang : 

" Now he is dead and will die no more, 

And we say so, for we know so. 
It makes his ribs feel very sore, 

Oh, poor old man. 
He is gone and will go no more, 

And we say so, &amp;c. 
So good-bye, old horse ! 

We.say good-bye ! " 

SOLO. Condolore. CHORUS. </lyrics>

?? 
 <commentary>
" It is in the superstitions of the sea that we must search 
for the beginning and history of many of the customs 
which in modified forms lingered down to the period of a 
late generation of seafarers. They veined the life with 
elements both of humour and romance, and I do not 
scruple to say that much of the poetry of the profession of 
the sea has perished with the extinction of the simple 
forecastle credulities of other ages. In the beginning of 
European navigation, in the times of Diaz, Cabot, Colum- 
bus, De Gama, and earlier yet, the mariner was a Roman 
Catholic, devout, profoundly superstitious, perpetually 
invoking the protection of the Blessed Virgin and the 
saints of heaven, finding miracles in the common opera- 
tions of nature, peopling the deep with wondrous monsters, 
glorifying its blue breast with the gleam and colour of the 
enchanted island, gazing awe-struck about him as. he sailed 
along, and willing to believe anything he was told. I 
could give you no better illustration of this than the 
remark of the Jesuit, Anthony Sepp, in his account of a 
voyage from Spain to Paraguana : ' Towards the evening,' 
says he, ' we saw an entire rainbow quite across the sky, 
resembling our rainbows.' Resembling our rainbows ! As 
though the worthy father supposed that rainbows in those 
unfamiliar seas were very different from the same radiant 
arches which span the showers of Italy, Spain, and 
Germany. They were prepared for all sorts of wonders, 
and their imaginations created what their eyes could not 
see. The lightning was not that of Europe ; the thunder 
was the reverberation of some hellish conflicts between 
armies formed of fiends of satanic stature ; the very rain 
was unnatural, being coloured. Religion, or superstition if 
you will, interposed to mitigate the horrors of a perfervid 
fancy, wrought familiar appearances into celestial expres- 
sions, and instructed poor Jack to calm his perturbed soul, 
to quell the tempest, to exorcise the mermaid, to smooth 
the waters, to disperse the horrid shadows of the electric 
storm with litanies, effigies of saints, and spells of many 
different sorts. Thus Pirard de Laval (in ' Churchill's 
Collection of Voyages,' vol. i., p. 702) says, * We frequently 
saw great whirlwinds rising at a distance, called by the 
seamen dragons, which shatter and overturn any ship that 
falls in their way. When these appear, the sailors have a 
superstitious custom of repairing to the prow, or the side 
that lies next the storm, and beating naked swords against 
one another crosswise.' This custom long prevailed, 
scores of similar practices may be traced to the primitive 
superstitions of sailors. They unquestionably colour the 
old marine life, and their extinction leaves the calling un- 
comfortably bald, I think. The stars in those aged stories 
seem to glow the richer for the incense floating up to them 
from the little altar on the forecastle, and for the tender 
strains of a hundred voices rising in some solemn melo- 
dious canticle : </commentary>

 <lyrics>' The night is calm and cloudless, 

And still as still can be, 
And the stars come forth to listen 

To the music of the sea. 
They gather, and gather, and gather, 

Until they crowd the sky, 
And listen in breathless silence 

To the solemn litany. 
It begins in rocky caverns 

As a voice that chants alone 
To the pedals of the organ 

In monotonous undertone ; 
And anon from shelving beaches 

And shallow ?ands beyond, 

In snow-white robes uprising 

The ghostly choirs respond. 
And sadly and unceasing 

The mournful voice sings on, 
And the snow-white choirs still answer, 

" Christe eleison ! " '</lyrics>

'The Golden Legend/ Longfellow. 

<quote>" The glory of the setting sun makes cloth of gold of the 
sails of those castellated fabrics, and they look to float 
over fairy seas of purple as we view them through that 
atmosphere of superstition, in the midst of which those 
young and awe-struck imaginations made their miracu- 
lous voyages to the Indies and to the mighty shores of 
Columbia." Clarke Russell. </quote>

<commentary>The legends of the water, whether of ocean, river, or 
lake, are so numerous that one might go on alluding to 
them for pages and never exhaust the subject. There is 
ample material for a volume in the weird tales of voices 
and bells sounding under the sea; but I think I have said 
enough to show that, apart from the sailors' songs and 
boatmen's chants that echo from end to end of the world 
of waters, there is an eternal strain of music which, day 
and night, and summer and winter, rises from the sea, and 
may fitly be termed " The Music of the Waters." </commentary>

<lyrics>" Oh, strangely glorious and beautiful sea ! 
Sounding for ever mysteriously, 
Why are thy billows still rolling on 
With their wild and sad and musical tone ? 
Why is there never repose for thee ? 
Why slumberest thou not, oh, mighty sea ? "</lyrics> </section>
 
<postamble>TO THE CRITICS. 

"Gentle breath of yours my sails must fill, 
Or else my project fails." 

LONDON : 

PRINTED BY GILBERT AND RIVINGTON, LIMITED, 
ST. JOHN'S HOUSE, CLERKENWELL ROAD. </postamble>
